Part two. You will hear a podcast by a running coach giving advice about taking up running
and giving information about her club. First, you have some time to look at questions eleven
to fourteen.
Now listen carefully and answer questions eleven to fourteen.
My name's Liz Fuller and I'm a running coach with Compton Park Runners Club. Welcome to
my podcast. If you're thinking about taking up running, I'm here to help. There are many
training programmes available online which aim to help people build up to running five
kilometres. Some of them are great and thousands of people of all ages are taking part in five-kilometre
races across the country as a result. People like them because they're easy to follow and
don't push them too hard. However, they don't work for everyone, especially if you suffer
from something like a heart condition or asthma, because they're aimed at people with average
fitness and running ability. Another thing is that everyone is different and if you have
any specific questions related to your needs, there's no one to provide any answers. I have
a couple of simple tips I always give to new runners. I expect you've been told to run
very slowly until your fitness increases. Well, I find that can prevent progress. You
should run at a speed that feels comfortable, but time yourself and try to run a bit faster
each time. Listening to music can be very helpful. It takes your mind off things and
helps your body get into a rhythm. I'd say that is better than running with a friend,
especially as most people are competitive and that's not what you want when you're
just starting. I don't think the time of day is especially important. Some people are better
in the evening, while others are morning people. But you need to be consistent, so aim to train
regularly. Twice a week is enough to begin with.
Before you hear the rest of the podcast, you have some time to look at questions 15 to 20.
Now listen and answer questions 15 to 20.
New members often say to me that they've been put off running either because they lack
confidence or they don't have time or they think they dislike running. Kerry, for example,
joined the club two years ago at the age of 40. She'd always enjoyed running at school
but wasn't sure if she'd be able to do it. She was worried about being left behind and
being the slowest runner. But she says she was made to feel so welcome she soon forgot
all about that. James had always hated the idea of running, but a friend encouraged him
to come along for a taster session and he hasn't looked back. He never misses a training
session despite having a really demanding job. Leo was worried about having to commit
himself to training sessions every week and wasn't sure he'd be able to fit training
into his busy schedule. But after experiencing a lot of stress at work, he came along to
us and gave it a go. Now he says he feels much more relaxed and he looks forward to
his weekly run. Mark is quite typical of our new members. He's never considered himself
to be a sporty person and it was only when he retired that he decided to take up the
challenge of trying to run five kilometres. It took him months to find the courage to
contact us but felt reassured immediately as there were other people his age who were
only just taking up running for the first time. My own journey hasn't been easy. I
did my first marathon when I was 37 after having had two kids. My husband had been running
marathons for years but I never dreamed I'd be doing one with him. I managed to complete
it in four hours but I felt like giving up halfway through. It was only the support of
the spectators that kept me going. I do think signing up for a race of whatever length is
motivating, whether it's 5k or 25k, because it's good to have something to work towards
and it gives you a sense of achievement. I did my first 10k after only six months which
was certainly very challenging and not something I'd necessarily recommend. But after you've
been training for a few weeks it's worth putting your name down for a 5k. Some people
find they only need a few practice runs before taking part in a race but I'd give yourself
a couple of months at least. Well, I hope that's given you a really good idea of what
to sign up for.